Finding Aid for Gunnar Birkerts and Associates, 1960-2014
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Photographic slides of projects
  - Woodbranch Energy Plaza, Houston, TX (1982)
    - Photographs of drawings and site by unknown photographer and Balthazar Korab, as stamped, 8 slides color (Box 87)
Faith & Form, Winter 1988-89, "Another Jewel in the Crown: St. Peter's Lutheran Church, Columbus, Indiana" by Kay Kaiser, pp. 9-13
L'Architettura (Italy), January 1989, "L'organico in verticale a 15 gradi," Domino's Tower, Ann Arbor, Michigan, pp. 2-3
Avots (Latvia), Nr. 2, Februaris 1989, "Architektura Ari Ir Sazinasanas Veids" (Architecture Also A Means of Communication), article on Gunnar Birkerts and various projects, pp. 32-37
Maksla (Latvia), Julijs-Augusts 1989, "Darbs Un Vertejums" (Work and Recognition), Profile of Gunnar Birkerts by Janis Dripe, p. 78
Sourcebook of Contemporary North American Architecture, From Postwar to Postmodern by Sylvia Hart Wright, pub. by Van Nostrand Reinhold, 1989; Federal Reserve Bank of Minneapolis; Fisher Administrative Center, University of Detroit; IBM Corporate Computer Center, Sterling Forest, New York; Law Library Addition, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor; Library and Dormitories, Tougaloo College, Tougaloo, Mississippi; Lincoln Elementary School, Columbus, Indiana, pp. 12-14, 151-152
The Architecture Library of the Future (Complexity and Contradictions), Peggy Ann Kusnerz, Editor, pub. by the University of Michigan Press, 1989; "Planning and Designing the Architectural Library" by Gunnar Birkerts, pp. 163-166
Groundworks, North American Underground Projects, 1980 to 1989, pub. by the American Underground-Space Association, Susan R. Nelson, Editor, 1989, "Law Library Addition, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Michigan," pp. 35-39
Karogs 4 (Latvia), pub. 1989, "Gunars Birkerts - Celtnes, projekti un domas" (Gunnar Birkerts - Buildings, Projects and Thoughts), pp. 174-179
The Architecture of Gunnar Birkerts text by Kay Kaiser, pub. by the American Institute of Architects Press and Centro Di della Edifimi, Florence, Italy, 1989
L'Arca (Italy), Ottobre 1989, "Un Canyon di Cristallo," Central Library Addition, University of California at San Diego, p. 101
Zvaigzne (Latvia), No. 20 - Oktobris 1989, "Gunars Birkerts, Riga," by Janis Krastins, pp. 2-3
Arquitectura Viva (Spain), Numero 8, Octubre 1989, "Duchamp juega al domino," Michigan, pp. 58-59
Maksla (Latvia), Novembris-Decembris 1989, "Un Elpojis...Architekturu" (Breathing Architecture), Essay on Gunnar Birkerts and his work by Janis Dripe, inside cover and pp. 30-33
Daugava 11 (Latvia), "The Architecture of Gunnar Birkerts," pub. 1989, pp. 32-33
L'Arca (Italy), Febbraio 1990, "Il Gotico Moderno di Gunnar Birkerts" (Gunnar Birkerts' Modern Gothic), St. Peter's Lutheran Church, Columbus, Indiana, 24-33
L'Arca (Italy), Marzo 1990, "Una scultura per abitare" (Sculpture for Living), Marge Monaghan House, Drummond Island, Michigan, pp. 60-63
L'Arca (Italy), Aprile 1990, "Un perimetro di cristallo per l'Universita di San Diego" (A Crystal Perimeter for San Diego University), Central Library Addition, University of California at San Diego, pp. 42-47
Zinatne Un Mes (Latvia - printed in both Latvian and Russian editions), No. 4, 1990, "Gaismas architekturas meistars" (Master of Architectural Lighting), inside cover and pp. 18-19
Interiors, May 1990, "Equity, Justice and Architecture," St. Peter's Lutheran Church and Lincoln Elementary School, Columbus, Indiana
Architecture, May 1990, "Safe Diplomacy," U.S. Embassy, Caracas, Venezuela, pp. 78-83
Faith & Form (Vol. XXIII), Spring 1990, "Design Questions," Church of St. Bede, Southfield, Michigan; University Reformed Church, Ann Arbor, Michigan; Cathedral of the Most Blessed Sacrament, Detroit, Michigan; Outdoor Chapel, Drummond Island, Michigan; Calvary Baptist Church, Detroit, Michigan; Outdoor Chapel, Latvian Center, Garezers, Three Rivers, Michigan, pp. 24-28
Architecture, September 1990, "European Forecast," Novoli Multi-Use Center, Florence, Italy, p. 60
Architectural Record, October 1990, "Birkerts Designs Turin Tower," Urban Center, Italgas Redevelopment Project, Torino, Italy, p. 19
Architecture, December 1990, "Patrons of Architecture" and "Domino's Effect," Domino's Tower and World Headquarters Building, Ann Arbor, Michigan; Marge Monaghan House and Outdoor Chapel, Drummond Island, Michigan; Prototypical Franchise Building, Jackson, Michigan, pp. 47-55, 127
L'Arca (Italy), December 1990, "La fortezza di luce," Latvian National Library, Riga, Latvia, pp. 97-98
Progressive Architecture, December 1990, "Inquiry: Religious Buildings," St. Peter's Lutheran Church, Columbus, Indiana, p. 84
L'Industria delle Costruzioni, December 1990, No. 230, "Un progetto di Gunnar Birkerts per Torino," Urban Center, Italgas Redevelopment Project, Torino, Italy, pp. 64-65
Karogs (Latvia), No. 12, 1990, "Gunars Birkerts, Latvijas Nacionalas Bibliotekas Projekts" (Gunnar Birkerts, Latvian National Library Project), 4-page insert between pp. 80-81
Architecture "Fundamental Issues" by Forrest Wilson, et al., pub. by Van Nostrand Reinhold, 1990; Federal Reserve Bank, pp. 16-17
L'Industria delle Costruzione, January 1991, No. 231, "Un progetto per la Biblioteca Lettone," Latvian National Library, Riga, Latvia, p. 54-55
Inland Architect, January/February 1991, "Birkerts Builds in Latvia" by Kay Kaiser, Latvian National Library, Riga, Latvia, p. 19
Immeubles de Bureaux (France) by Marc Bedarida and Milka Milatovic, pub. by Editions du Moniteur, Paris, 1991, "Domino's Pizza, Ann Arbor, Michigan," 70-75
L'Arca (Italy), March 1991, "L'architettura e impegno," Latvian National Library, Riga, Latvia, pp. 72-78
Zodiac 5 (Italy), March 1991, "Multi-Functional Building in Novoli, Florence," 204-205
Maksla (Latvia), April 1991, "Kur Noenkurosim Gramatu Kugi..." (Where Should We Anchor the Ship of Books?) by Janis Dripe, National Library, Riga, Latvia, pp. 50-55
Modern Steel Construction, May 1991, "Leaning High-Rise Buildings," Domino's Farms Tower, Ann Arbor, Michigan, pp. 17-23
L'Architettura (Italy), May 1991, "Oberlin College, Ohio: Ampliamento della Biblioteca del Conservatorio" (Conservatory of Music Library Addition) and "Ann Arbor, Michigan University: servize sportivi" (Sports Services Building), pp. 452-462
Inland Architect, May/June 1991, "Reinterpretations: An examination of the contemporary legacy of the Prairie School" by Dennis McFadden, Domino's Farms, Ann Arbor, Michigan, pp. 30-37
Architectural Record, July 1991, "Most Important Buildings, 1891-1991," Federal Reserve Bank of Minneapolis, pp. 266-267
Architectural Record, August 1991, "New Work by Gunnar Birkerts" by Margaret Gaskie, U.S. Embassy, Caracas, Venezuela; Novoli Mixed-Use Center, Florence, Italy; National Library, Riga, Latvia; Mixed-Use Center, Turin, Italy; University of Torino, Turin, Italy, pp. cover, 64-75
American Baltic News, October 1991, "A Place of Learning...A Place to Be," National Library, Riga, Latvia, p. 9
100 Contemporary Architects, Drawings & Sketches, selected by Bill Lacy, pub. by Harry N. Abrams, Inc., New York, 1991; "Gunnar Birkerts," pp. 34-35
Architectural Drawing: Options for Design by Paul Laseau, pub. by Design Press, 1991; Anchorage Library Competition, Anchorage, Alaska; Ferguson Residence, Kalamazoo, Michigan; University of Michigan Law Library Addition; Lincoln Elementary School, Columbus, Indiana; Freeman Residence, Grand Rapids, Michigan, pp. 10, 11, 51,145
Inland Architect, November/December 1991, "Kansas City to Get New Museum" by Barbara K. Hower, Museum of Contemporary Art and Design/Kansas City Art Institute, pp. 56-57
American Architects and the Mechanics of Fame by Roxanne Kuter Williamson, pub. by the University of Texas Press, 1991, pp. 3, 96, 128, 131 189, 234, 240
SD (Space Design) (Japan), December 1991, National Library, Riga, Latvia, p.112
The San Diego Union-Tribune, February 16, 1992, "Let there be light!" by Kay Kaiser, Central Library Addition, University of California, San Diego, F-1 & F-10
Architectural Record-Review - Educational Buildings, 1991/1992, "University of Iowa College of Law, 1987," pp. cover, 24-32
Costruire (Italy), No. 106, March 1992, "Intervista a Birkerts - L'Ammiraglia del Baltico" (Birkerts Relaunches the Baltics) by Fabrizio Bonomo, National Library, Riga, Latvia, pp. 7, 9, 186-188
Progressive Architecture, September 1992, "Latter-Day Expressionists" by Philip Arcidi, Urban Center and University of Torino, Torino, Italy, pp. 112-114
Neuf (Belgium), October/November 1992, "Gunnar Birkerts: Organic Synthesis," Interview with Gunnar Birkerts, pp. 34-35
Costruire (Italy), No. 115, December 1992, "Sottoterra con vista," Holtzman & Silverman Office Building, Southfield, Michigan, pp. 160-163
L'Industria delle Costruzioni (Italy), February 1993, No. 256, "Un progetto per il nuovo stadio di Venezia," Stadium, Venice, Italy, p. 61
American Architecture: Ideas and Ideologies in the Late Twentieth Century by Paul Heyer, pub. by Van Nostrand Reinhold, New York, 1993; Fire Station, Corning, New York; Dance Instructional Facility, SUNY, Purchase, New York; College of Law, University of Iowa; Museum of Glass, Corning, New York; Tougaloo College Library, Tougaloo, Mississippi; Federal Reserve Bank of Minneapolis; IBM Corporate Computer Center, Sterling Forest, New York, pp. 23-24, 39, 57-58, 62-63, 90
Whitney Guide: 20th Century American Architecture: 200 Key Buildings by Sydney LeBlanc, pub. by Whitney Library of Design, an imprint of Watson-Guptill Publications, New York, 1993; Federal Reserve Bank of Minneapolis, p. 141
Underground Space Design: A Guide to Subsurface Utilization and Design for People in Underground Spaces by John Carmody and Raymond Sterling, pub. by Van Nostrand Reinhold, New York, 1993; Law Library Addition, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor; Uris Library Addition, Cornell University, Ithaca, New York, pp. 185,186, 194, 270
Understanding Architecture, Its Elements, History and Meaning by Leland M. Roth, pub. by Harper Collins, New York, 1993; Federal Reserve Bank of Minneapolis, p. 40
Architecture in the 20th Century by Udo Kultermann, pub. by Van Nostrand Reinhold, New York, 1993; Federal Reserve Bank of Minneapolis; Tougaloo College Library, Mississippi; Law School Addition, University of Michigan, pp. 120, 122, 195, 196
Linguaggi dell'Architettura Contemporanea by Bruno Zevi, pub. by Etaslibri, Italy, 1993; Museum of Glass, Corning, New York (Project No. 48)
L'Architettura (Italy), December 1993, "Gunnar Birkerts: frenzy, landscape and repertory in three works," Kemper Museum of Contemporary Art and Design, Kansas City, Missouri; Holtzman-Silverman Office Building, Southfield, Michigan; Town House, Birmingham, Michigan
L'Arca (Italy), January 1994, No. 78, "From Library to City," Marriott Library Expansion, University of Utah, Salt Lake City, and "The Dynamic Museum," Museum of Contemporary Art and Design, Kansas City, Missouri, pp. 78-81, 97
Costruire (Italy), May 1994, "Luce nel sottosuolo" by Fabrizio Bonomo and Monica Racic, Central Library Addition, University of California, San Diego, 151-153
Between Lines: From Doodles to Composition by Anupam Banerji and Michael Elmitt, pub. by Escart Press, Faculty of Environmental Studies, University of Waterloo, Ontario, 1994; Urban Center, Torino, Italy, pp. 22, 181
Process and Expression in Architectural Form by Gunnar Birkerts, pub. by The University of Oklahoma Press, Norman, 1994
Arbitare (Italy), September 1994, "University: an A-Z guide to projects and latest buildings," College of Law Addition/Renovation, Ohio State University, Columbus, p. 176
L'Architettura (Italy), September 1994, "Una casa in Colorado," Grasis Residence, Vail, Colorado, pp. 624-626
L'Industria delle Costruzioni (Italy), November 1994, "Argomenti" (Topics), Library, University of Michigan, Flint, p. 82
Encyclopedia of American Architecture, Second Edition, Robert T. Packard and Balthazar Korab, Editors, pub. by McGraw-Hill, Inc., 1995, pp. 43-45, 125, 138, 380, 470, 603, 647, 648, 661, 684
Hinge (Hong Kong), December/January 1995, Vol. 15, "Through the Looking Glass," Kemper Museum of Contemporary Art and Design, Kansas City Art Institute, Missouri, pp. 28-30
Architecture & Urbanism (Japan), March 1995, No. 294, "Gunnar Birkerts: College of Law Addition/Renovation, The Ohio State University," 35-67
L'Industria delle Costruzioni (Italy), No. 280, February 1995, "Ampliamento dell'Universita' dell'Ohio" (The Renovated College of Law, Ohio State University), pp. cover, 2, 34-39
World Architecture (England), 1995, No. 36, "Profile; Gunnar Birkerts," projects include Central Library Expansion, University of California, San Diego; Sports Services Building, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor; College of Law Addition/Renovation, Ohio State University, Columbus; Novoli Multi-Use Center, Florence, Italy; Church of the Servant, Kentwood, Michigan; National Library, Riga, Latvia; U.S. Embassy, Caracas, Venezuela; Grasis House, Vail, Colorado; Humanities Faculties Building, University of Turin, Italy; Library, University of Michigan, Flint; Kemper Museum of Contemporary Art and Design, Kansas City, Missouri; Performing Arts Center, Michigan Technological University, Houghton, pp. cover, 23-53
Progressive Architecture, November 1995, "News - Projects: An Eye to the View," Thompson Library, University of Michigan-Flint, p. 24
L'Arca (Italy), November 1995, No. 98, "Museo a Kansas City," Kemper Museum of Contemporary Art and Design," Kansas City, Missouri, pp. 20-27
Engineering News-Record, December 4, 1995, "Bank builds on its history," Federal Reserve Bank of Minneapolis, p. 17
Architecture in North America Since 1960 by Alexander Tzonis, Liane Lefaivre and Richard Diamond, pub. by Little, Brown and Co., Canada, 1995; Contemporary Arts Museum, Houston, Texas and Federal Reserve Bank of Minneapolis, pp. 47, 49, 146, 147
Architecture & Urbanism (Japan), January 1996, No. 304, "Gunnar Birkerts; Frances Willson Thompson Library, University of Michigan-Flint," pp. 3, 56-63
L'Industria Italiana del Cemento (Italy), March 1996, No. 708, La Jolla: Ampliamento Sotterraneo della Biblioteca dell'Universita della California," Central Library Addition, University of California, San Diego, pp. 170-179
Latvijas Arhitektura (Latvia), May 1996, "Bankas eka ka pazisanas zime," Federal Reserve Bank of Minneapolis, Minnesota, pp. 32-33
Interiors, July 1996, "Project Briefs," Pilliing Chapel, Millikin University, Decatur, Illinois, p. 29
City Business, September 13-15, 1996, Vol. 14, No. 15, "Old Fed Building Shows Promise" by Lynn Keillor, Federal Reserve Bank of Minneapolis, Minnesota, pp. 26-27
Architecture, September 1996, "On the Boards," Pilling Chapel, Millikin Uiversity, Decatur, Illinois, p. 56 and "New Commissions," Market Master Plan, Riga, Latvia, p. 49
Modern American Houses: Four Decades of Award-Winning Design in Architectural Record, edited by Clifford A. Pearson, pub. by Harry N. Abrams, Inc., NY, 1996, Freeman House, Grand Rapids, Michigan, pp. 54,55
AIArchitect, December 1996, Vol. 3, "A Driving Force in Columbus" by Eric Adams, St. Peter's Lutheran Church, Columbus, Indiana, p. 23 and "Components Honor Achievement," AIA Michigan Awards, p. 14
Library Journal, December 1996, Frances Willson Thompson Library, University of Michigan-Flint, pp. 44, 45
Urban-Suburban: The Architecture of Purchase College (Exhibition Booklet), Neuberger Museum of Art, Purchase College, State University of New York, Dance Instructional Facility, September 22, 1996 - January 19, 1997
New Public Architecture by Jeremy Myerson, pub. by Laurence King Pub., London, 1996, Kemper Museum of Contemporary Art and Design, Kansas City, Missouri, pp. 138-141
Glass in Architecture by Michael Wigginton, pub. by Phaidon Press, Ltd., London, 1996, Corning Museum of Glass, Corning, New York, pp. 99, 116-121
Zevi Su Zevi (Italy), 1993, "Firenze 2000," p.117, mention p. 186
Storia dell'Architettura Moderna by Bruno Zevi, 1996, Federal Reserve Bank of Minneapolis, pp. 453, 682
L'Industria Italiana delle Costruzioni (Italy), Marzo 1997, No. 305, Frances Willson Thompson Library, University of Michigan-Flint, pp. 36-43
Architectural Record, July 1997, "Gunnar Birkerts Returns Home to Riga by Designing Two Major Projects," p. 28
L'Architettura (Italy), 1997, No. 488, Biblioteca Michigan, Flint, Museo D'Arte Contemporaea E Design, Kansas City
World Architecture, October 1997, No. 60, "A Lore Unto Himself," Latvian National Library, p. 40
Architectural Record, November 1997, "Lightning Strikes in Michigan," AirTouch Cellular Tower, p. 46
World Architecture, November 1997, No. 61, "It's Good to Talk," AirTouch Cellular Tower, Ann Arbor, Michigan, p. 17
Architecture Today by James Steele, pub. by Phaidon Press, Ltd., London, "The New Expressionists," 1997, pp. 254-259
Gli Architetti, No. 33, "Gunnar Birkerts Metafore Ed Espansioni Sottoterranee" by Kay Kaiser, pub. by Testo & Immagine, 1997
Latvijas Arhitektura (Latvia), Aprilis 1998, No. 16, "Gunars Birkerts Un Gaisma," pp. 4-13
L'Arca (Italy), June 1998, No. 127, "Anarchia Tecnologica," AirTouch Cellular Tower, Ann Arbor, Michigan, pp. 84-85
Progetto (Italy), Giugno 1998, No. 3, AirTouch Cellular Tower, Ann Arbor, Michigan, pp. 22-23
L'Espresso (Italy), "Antenne Scolpite" by Bruno Zevi, AirTouch Cellular Tower, Ann Arbor, Michigan
I Quaderni di Mirage (Italy), 1998, No. 5, "Gunnar Birkerts: Below the Surface, the Subzero Level," Landscaping and the Zero Degree Language of Architecture, First International Convention, pp. 26-31
Art and Antiques, September 1998, "House of Glass," Lewis Residence, pp. 64-69
Architectural Record, September 1998, "Smith-Miller & Hawkinson's Addition to the Corning Glass Center Connects to the Past While Pointing to Future Growth" by Clifford Pearson, Corning Museum of Glass, p. 124-131
The Architectural Review (United Kingdom), October 1998, "Bolt from the Blue," AirTouch Cellular Tower, Ann Arbor, Michigan, pp. 32-33
Architectural Record, January 1999, letter from Gunnar Birkerts: "Don't Save Icon by Changing It," Federal Reserve Bank of Minneapolis, p. 20
L'Architettura (Italy), March 1999, No. 523, "Biblioteca Marriott Ampliamento," Marriott Library Addition, University of Utah, Salt Lake City, pp. 286-291
Latvijas Arhitektura, June 1999, No. 23 (3), "Grasa Maja," Grasis Residence, Vail, Colorado, pp. 9-11
World Architecture, July/August 1999, No. 78, "UNESCO Saves Latvian Landmark," p. 50
Latvijas Arhitektura, August 1999, No. 24 (4), "Latvijas Nacionala Biblioteka" by Dr. arch. Janis Lejnieks, pp. 28-36, Architecture, September 1999, "Rear-View Mirror: Smith-Miller & Hawkinson's Crystalline Addition to the Corning Museum of Glass Looks Back as It Looks Forward" by Ned Cramer, GB mention, p. 94
Architectural Record, September 1999, "Record News - San Jose Building an Unusual Multiuse Library," p. 74
L'Architettura (Italy), September 1999, Nuova Serie - anno III, n. 26-29, "Gunnar Birkerts: Everything was explored except the subsoil," pp. 422-427
Paesaggistica e Linguaggio Grado Zero dell'Architettura (Landscape and the Zero Degree of Architectural Language) (Italy) by Bruno Zevi, No. 503-506, pub. by Canal & Stamperia Editrice, September 1999, "Gunnar Birkerts: Everything was explored except the subsoil," pp. 422-427
World Architecture, October 1999, No. 80, "Analysis - Prodigious Prodigals (Gunnar Birkerts and Kevin Roche: the return of the prodigal sons to Latvia and Ireland)," pp. 38-39
Baltic Outlook (Latvia), October/November 1999, "Riga's Crystal Palace," pp. 54-57
Architecture for the Gods by Michael J. Crosbie, pub. by The Images Publishing Group, Pty. Ltd., 1999, St. Peter's Lutheran Church, Columbus, Indiana, pp. 168-169
L'Arca (Italy), October 1999, No. 141, "Biblioteca Ipogea," Marriott Library, University of Utah, Salt Lake City, pp. 76-79
L'Industria Italiana del Cemento (Italy), January 2000, No. 1, "Museo d'Arte Contemporanea e Design a Kansas City," Kemper Museum of Contemporary Art, Kansas City, Missouri, pp. 9-13
Baumeister (Germany), February 2000, "Transatlantisch Baltisch" (Transatlantic Baltic), Latvian National Library, p. 8
Architectural Record, February 2000, "Correspondent's File/Fearing runaway sprawl, Silicon Valley heads downtown" by Eric C. Y. Fang, Joint Library, San Jose, California, P. 46
Hauser (Germany), March 2000, "Zauberberg fur Riga" (Magic Mountain for Riga), p. 14
Wallpaper (United Kingdom), June 2000, "Switching On to Books," Latvian National Library, Riga, p. 37
Worth, August 2000, "The Economy of Modernism" by Hillary Johnson, St. Peter's Lutheran Church, Columbus, Indiana, p. 91
Zoo (United Kingdom), November 2000, "Gunnar Birkerts' Latvian National Library," pp. 128-129
Wallpaper (United Kingdom), October 2000, "Speaking Volumes" by Alexandria Abramian, Geisel Library Addition, University of California, San Diego
Architecture, July 2005, "Gunnar Birkerts's Organic Lifestyle" by Martin Schwartz, pp. 20-24